Register of the Joseph C. Trainor papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Joseph C. Trainor papers
1933-1980
72022
Hoover Institution Archives
76 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes, 1 album box, 1 sound tape reel (37.1 linear feet)
Writings, memoranda, reports, surveys, handbooks, maps, photographs, and printed matter relating to education reform in Japan during the Allied occupation. Includes sound recording of interview of J. C. Trainor by Harry Wray, 1980. Also available on microfilm (66 microfilm reels).
Trainor, Joseph C.
Wray, Harry.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (66 microfilm reels).
Biographical Note
Jospeh C. Trainor was made a lieutenant commander of the United States Army in May of 1946. For one year, until May of 1947, he served as a member of the Education Division of the Civil Information and Education Section of the General Headquarters of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers in Tokyo. He returned in July of 1949 in the capacity of Deputy Chief of the Education Division. The occupation authorities in Japan were committed to a program of democratizing Japan. One important facet of this program was educational reform. Occupation authorities rigorously pursued a program of restructuring administrative machinery, reorganizing schools, and reforming curricula. As a staff member of the Education Division for one year in 1946 to 1947, Trainor became familiar with this endeavor. As its Deputy Chief and second-in-command from July of 1949 until the American authorities left Japan in 1952, he was intimately involved at the policy and implementation levels.
Scope and Content Note
The Joseph C. Trainor papers reflect and document the program of democratization American authorities pursued vis-a-vis the Japanese educational system. Rather than an arbitrary assemblage of an individual's papers, the Trainor papers comprises archives, possibly incomplete, of American governmental and other agencies. The three series -- Ministry of Education File; Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers (SCAP). General Headquarters (GHQ). Civil and Information Section (CIE) File; and Subject File -- conform to the arrangment of the collection when it arrived at the Hoover Institution Archives. Within the series, the original arrangement of files has been maintained to as great an extent as possible while still insuring a logical and accessible organization. Within the three series are found many types of material ranging from handwritten notes to reprints of American journal articles. The series description which follows gives a more detailed inventory of the types of documents.
The Ministry of Education File consists primarily of copies of documents, typescripts usually, which were generated either by the Japanese Ministry of Education or by other administrative or legislative bodies, such as the Diet. These documents usually define, but occasionally establish, the functions of the Ministry.
The second series, the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, General Headquarters, Civil Information and Education File, comprises over 80% of the collection. This series is then further broken down into subseries, the largest and most important of which is titled Education Division. The subseries represent distinctions found within the collection when it arrived at the repository. Throughout the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers... series, the researcher will find reports, memoranda, statistics, studies and a host of other material relating to the effort of reorganizing Japanese education.
The last series is the Subject File. It, too, contains a variety of forms of documents. To a limited extent, documents from sections of the Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, General Headquarters other than Civil Information and Education are to be found in this series. Some documents pertain to education. The majority of documents in this file, however, are unrelated to education, and concern a variety of topics.
In all of the series, files are arranged alphabetically by subject or title, following closely the original arrangement of the collection when it was received. If materials are dated, the dates are given at the end of an entry. A dash between two dates indicates there is material in the file covering that time span. A comma, however, is used to indicate materials form two different days, months or years, with no material from the intervening period in the file. Single items missing a date are listed with "undated" at the end of their entry. Folders with dates given may contain material which is undated, in which case that material has been placed at the back of the folder. If under a single entry with large quantities of material, enough material was undated to warrant its own folder, it is listed as the last subheading of that entry as "undated." The purpose behind the positioning of undated material at the end of a file, or files, was to give the researcher a better chance of understanding, if not actually placing, undated materials after reading through the sequence of dated material.
Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers.; Education--Japan.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Audiotapes.
- Microfilm Reel Content Guide
  Other Finding Aids note
  Downloadable PDF file of the Microfilm Reel Content Guide
- Ministry of Education File, 1937-1952
  Scope and Contents note
  Memoranda, reports, studies, surveys, and other printed material either generated by or pertaining to the Japanese Ministry of Education, arranged alphabetically by subject or title, and thereunder chronologically.
  - General
    - The Activities of UNICEF School Lunch Program in Japan. Report, 1951 February (Box 1)
    - The Authorization Standard for Textbook. Book of standards published by the Ministry of Education, 1949 January 12
    - Board of Education - 10th General Meeting, 1951 September
    - Bricks Without Straw - examples of classes which are improperly housed, 1950 September 15
    - Budget items for in-service training of educational personnel, report, 1949-1950
    - Cardinal Principles of the National Entity of Japan, translation by J. O. Gauntlett, 1937 March
    - The Condition of School in the Local Districts Suffering from the Shortage of Schoolrooms. Report, undated
      - Part I
      - Part II
    - Copyright Investigation Committee. Cabinet order, draft, 1950 April 20
    - Decentralization (tentative). Memo, 1946 June 7
    - Display of national flags. Memo, 1946 September 26
    - Education finance - Education Costs Compared with Non-Education Costs. Report, 1951 October
    - Educational magazines. List, 1945 September (Box 2)
    - Elementary school history course readers, 5th and 6th grades, undated
    - Establishment law, 1946 May 31
    - Field surveys of local educational expenditures, 1950 August
    - Fundamental education law. Draft, 1947 January 30
    - Guide to New Education in Japan, published by the Ministry of Education. Vol. 1, Pt. A, 1946
    - Handbooks on curriculum, execution, organization and principals of schools, 1947, 1951
    - Handling of Labor Problems after General McArthur's Letter. Memo, 1948 September 4
    - Institute for Educational Leadership - Budget, 1951-1952
    - Institute for Research in Language Teaching - Report on its history, object and policy, 1946 January 27
    - Japanese History for Normal School, by Norizo Takeuchi. Vol. A, Chaps. 1 - 5
    - Korean schools, 1948-1949
    - Laws and ordinances, 1947-1948
    - Local Educational Expenditures in Japan, 1949-1950 - Report of a National Survey, 1951
    - National Conference of Social Education Advisory Committee Members, 1951 October
    - Organization and personnel, 1945-1946
    - Outline of the Bureau of Indoctrination. Outline of book, 1938 March (Box 3)
    - Primer of Democracy, 1948 October 30
    - Proposed Examining Standard of English Textbooks, by R. Shisito, 1948 April
    - Report on the Execution of Exhibition of Textbooks for 1951 School Year, 1950 September
    - Report on Conditions of Textbook Exhibitions as of August 1949, 1949 October 31
    - Report to Minister on the United States of America, by Kaoro Sato, Chief of Educational Facilities Section, 1951 May 31
    - School education law, 1947-1948
    - Selection of Japanese delegate to the 1952 New York Herald-Tribune forum for high schools. Memo, 1951
    - Subsidies to Equipment Expenses for the Science, Mathematics, Nursing, and Health Protection Courses for Secondary Schools. Report, 1946 November 21
    - Survey of school building needs in Japan. Report, 1949 September 6
    - A Tentative Suggested Course of Study (General). Report, 1947
    - Textbooks, 1945-1950
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1952
  - Bureau of Science and Health Education
    - Literature Team List of Foreign Publications Desired by Universities in Japan. Report, 1950 November
    - Literature Team List of Foreign Publications Desired by Universities in Japan, Back Issues. Report, 1950 November (Box 4)
    - Survey of Traditional Customs in Various Districts, 1946 November 15
    - Teaching Materials Section - An Investigation of Superstition, undated
  - Coordinating Office for the Seminar
    - List of participants in the Seminar of Superintendents and Teacher Consultants, 1950 March - May
  - Elementary and Secondary Education Bureau
    - Finance for elementary and secondary education, 1950 August
  - Higher Education and Science Bureau
    - Natural Science Research Activities and Statistics on Researchers in Japan. Report, 1950
  - Research Bureau
    - Report of the Survey on Mobility of Teachers in Elementary and "New System" Intermediate Schools, 1947 December 1
    - School basic survey, 1948-1949
    - School hygiene survey, 1940-1949 (Box 5)
    - School teacher survey, 1947
  - Research Section
    - Gist of the Conference for Research of Educational Affairs in Foreign Countries. Memo, 1947 July 24 (Box 6)
    - Local expenditures in Japan, 1950-1951
    - Outline of Works in the Research Section, Research Bureau, 1948 September 15
    - The Reasons for the Necessity of Research and Statistics Bureau. Memo, 1948 September 1
    - Research cases for each bureau and section, 1948 September 15
  - Research and Publications Bureau
    - Annual Program of Research and Statistics of Each Section of the Bureau of Education Ministry. Report, fiscal year, 1950
    - Reasons why Personnel Organization of Educational Personnel Must Be the Federation of Municipal Unit Organizations. Report, 1946 February 26
- Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers (SCAP). General Headquarters (GHQ). Civil Information and Education Section (CIE) File, 1943-1952
  Memoranda, reports, correspondence, minutes, transcripts, studies, lists, surveys, statistical tables, press releases, and other printed material generated by or pertaining to the Civil Information and Education Section or any one of its subordinate bureaus or offices, arranged alphabetically by subject or title, and thereunder chronologically.
  - General
    - Administrative staff memorandum, 1945 December 27 (Box 6)
    - Committee on Missions and Functions, undated
    - Directory of Boards of Education and Superintendents of Education, 1951 September 1
    - Mission and Accomplishments of the Occupation in the Civil Information and Education Fields. Report, 1950 January 1
    - Monthly reports
      - 1947 July
      - 1947 September
      - 1947 October
      - 1948 January
      - 1948 February
      - 1948 March
      - 1948 April
      - 1948 May
      - 1948 June
      - 1948 July
      - 1948 August
    - Monthly summary, 1951 May 15 (Box 7)
    - Orientation pamphlet, 1947 February
    - Personnel chart, 1947 October 7
    - Report of the United States Cultural Science Mission to Japan, 1949 January
    - Report to Dr. Loomis on Trip to America, by M. Kawano, Superintendent of Education, Tokushima Board of Education, 1950 July 10
    - Tokai-Hokuriki regional office - Administrative survey of Futaba Koto Gakko, Kami-Suwa City, Nagano Prefecture. Report, 1951 December 22
    - Tokyo Military Government Team, Relations with. Memo, 1948 June 30
    - Miscellaneous
  - Analysis and Research Division
    - Activities of the National Teachers Unions from 1 May to 1 October 1946: Union and Disunion. Special report, 1946 October 23
    - Appointment of Government Officials under the Civil Service System as of 1 April 1946. Special report, 1946 October 9
    - A Calendar of Teacher's Salary Campaign, September to December, 1946. Special report, 1947 January 29
    - Current Japanese Public Opinion Surveys. No. 2, 1948 June 5
    - Economic Aid to Students in Japan. Special report, 1948 May 10
    - Educational Institutions Not Under the Jurisdiction of the Ministry of Education. Report, 1947 January
    - Educational Prefectures - Rosters and Statistics, 1946 April - November
      - Aichi
      - Akita
      - Aomori
      - Chiba
      - Ehime
      - Fukui (Box 8)
      - Fukuoka
      - Fukushima
      - Gifu
      - Gumma
      - Hiroshima
      - Hokkaido
      - Hyogo
      - Ibaraki
      - Ishikawa
      - Iwate (Box 9)
      - Kagawa
      - Kagoshima
      - Kanagawa
      - Kochi
      - Kumamoto
      - Kyoto
      - Mie
      - Miyagi
      - Miyazaki
      - Nagano
      - Nagasaki
      - Nara
      - Niigata (Box 10)
      - Oita
      - Okayama
      - Osaka
      - Saga
      - Saitama
      - Shiga
      - Shimane
      - Shizvoka
      - Tochigi
      - Tokushima
      - Tokyo-to (Box 11)
      - Tottori
      - Toyama
      - Wakayama
      - Yamagata
      - Yamaguchi
      - Yamanashi
    - Elementary School System, Outline of Conditions in. Special report, 1946 August 28
    - Entrance Examinations in Japanese Education. Special report, 1946 July 3
    - Foreign Students in Japan. Special report, 1946 September 23
    - Foreign Students in Japan, 1896-1947. Report, 1948 April 20
    - Higher Educational Institutions in Japan. Special report, 1948 February 23 - October 13
    - Historical Section for the new education brochure - Analysis of the Development of the Educational System of Japan through World War II, written as a background section for the education brochure, 1946 April 11
    - A History of the Educational Policy of the Ministry of Education as Evidenced by Directives and Instructions 1871 - 1945. Special report, 1946 November 20
    - History of the Ministry of Education, 1868-1941, 1946 August 19
    - Japan Young Men's Hostel. Special report, 1947 February 17 (Box 12)
    - Japanese Educational Institutions Under the Jurisdiction of Ministries Other than the Ministry of Education. Special report, 1948 April 30
    - Japanese Educational Institutions With Religious Affiliations. Report, 1948 February 20
    - Japanese Educational Research Organizations, 1946-1947, A Survey of, 1946 October 28
    - The Japanese Ministry of Education, Part I: The Place of the Ministry of Education in the Structure of the National School System. Special report, 1948 March 26 - August 9
    - Japanese Semmon Gakko. Special report, 1946 December 3
    - Japanese teachers' unions, 1946
    - Libraries in Japan. Special report, 1947 March 28
    - Members prominent in education elected to the lower house of the Diet. Statistical table, 1946 June 12
    - Military government school inspection reports, monthly compilation of. Memo, 1947 April 2
    - The Ministry of Education in Relation to the Ministry of Home Affairs, Finance, War and Navy During World War II. Special report, 1947 January 8
    - National Teachers' Unions of Japan, Membership. Special report, 1946 November 15
    - New Women's Educational Institutions Since the Beginning of the Occupation. Check sheet, 1946 October 28
    - The Organizational Development of the Ministry of Education. Special report, 1946 September 12
    - Parent-Teacher Associations in Japan. Special report, 1946 November 25
    - Physical Education Conferences Held During the Month of July. Special report, 1946 August 30
    - The Place of the Teachers Unions in the General Labor Situation. Special report, 1947 April 25
    - Press and publications analyses, 1948 February, June and October
    - Questions from teachers throughout Japan. Survey, 1948 August 8
    - Reeducation of Japanese Ex-servicemen. Report, 1946 July 25
    - Reference card catalog of materials on Japanese education published by the Education Division, 1946 October 29
    - Religious Education Institutions in Japan. Report, 1947 August 21
    - Reports on Screened Teachers. Check sheet, 1946 August 28
    - Research unit reports, 1947 February - December
    - School Inspection System of Japan. Report, 1948 March 30
    - Survey of Japanese Higher Educational Institutions. Special report, 1946 October 30 (Box 13)
    - Survey of School Housing Facilities as of August 1946. Statistical tables, 1947 January - April
    - Survey of Student Aid Facilities and Procedures. Special report, 1946 December 12 (Box 14)
    - Teacher Training in Keio Private University for Justice. Special report, 1947 February 25
    - Teacher Training in Kyoto Imperial University. Special report, 1947 February 6
    - Teacher Training in Kyushu Imperial University. Special report, 1947 February 12
    - Teacher Training in Tohoku Imperial University. Special report, 1947 February 20
    - Teacher Training in Tokyo Imperial University. Special report, 1947 February 17
    - Teacher Training in Tokyo University of Literature and Science. Special report, 1947 January 7
    - Teachers Unions: A Year Demands and Results, December 1945 - December 1946. Report, 1947 January 8
    - Teachers Unions and Similar Organizations in the Prefectures of Japan. Report, 1946 November 18
    - Teachers Unions in Japan, A History of. Special report, 1948 March 25
    - Tokyo Teachers Unions - Financial Statements. Special report, 1946 December 18
    - Tsuda College: A Study by Fumi Kawase, 1946 December 11
    - Weekly reports
      - 1946 February - June
      - 1946 July - December
      - 1947 January - August
      - 1947 September - 1948 October (Box 15)
    - Women Admitted into the Imperial Universities of Japan. Special report, 1946 December 5
  - Civil Affairs Section
    - Civil Education. Directive, 1951 April 2
  - Diplomatic Section
    - Reference List of the Allied Council for Japan, Accredited Diplomatic Missions and Diplomatic Section of SCAP, GHQ, 1950 September 20
  - Economic and Scientific Section
    - Science and Technology in Japan: Natural Research in Leading Japanese Universities, Part I. Report No. 16, 1949 June
  - Education Division
    - Action papers, 1948-1949
    - Administration - Instruction and programs, 1948 January
    - Administration of Education at the Primary and Secondary Levels, Chapter VII
    - Administration survey of Kita Koko Gakko, Ogaki City, Gifu prefecture, 1951 November - December
    - Adult education, 1946 July - 1950 August
    - The Adult Education Program, Chapter XIV
    - Advisory Council for Guidance and Welfare Institute. Minutes of meetings, 1951 June 21 and July 6
    - The Aims of Education, Chapter I
    - All-Japan Conference of Teachers Unions - Collective contract, 1947 March
    - All-Japan Teachers Guild regulations, revision of. Study, undated
    - American Advisory Group to Japan. Minutes of meetings, 1946 February
    - American Teachers in Japan. List, 1951 April 10
    - American sponsored schools and colleges in Japan, points on which information is desired. Memo, 1949 May 10
    - Annex E Military Government reports, 1948
    - Assignments of Education and Youth Officers. List, undated
    - Audio-visual education, 1948 January - 1951 May (Box 16)
    - Audio-Visual Teaching Materials, Chapter III
    - Bi-weekly reports
      - 1951 May - June
      - 1951 July
      - 1951 August
      - 1951 September - October
      - 1951 November
      - 1951 December - 1952 January
    - Board of Education law
      - 1946-1947 (Box 17)
      - 1948-1951
    - Boards of Control in 47 private Japanese universities. Research report, 1949 February - March
    - Boards of Control in private universities - Survey questionnaires, 1949 February 12 - March 22
    - Boards of Education
      - 1948
      - 1949-1951
    - Books banned by the Imperial Japanese Government. Memoranda, 1946 January
    - Boy Scout organizations, 1947 April - 1951 October
    - Briefing of publishers and editors. Memo, 1947 January 28
    - Budget, 1947-1950
    - Cabinet Order Concerning the Temporary Measures to be Taken in Consequence of the Letter of the SCAP to the Prime Minister dated 22 July 1948. Typescript (Box 18)
    - Catholic student organizations. List, 1949 September
    - Chiba student government conference. Program, 1950 July
    - Civil affairs teams, 1948 August
    - Civil Education
      - General, 1945-1950
      - Conferences, 1947-1949
      - Report, 1949
      - Survey, undated
    - Civilian personnel, 1948-1952
    - Class size in elementary and secondary schools. Memo, undated
    - COA Conference, 1950 September 30
    - Coeducation, 1946, 1948
    - Comments on book Goals for American Education, 1948-1949
    - Communism and subversive activities in Japanese education, 1946 December - 1951 January
    - Complete list of books in CIE Textbook and Curriculum Center Library, 1949 July 1
    - Coordination between NRS and CIE, 1950
    - Counseling and guidance for students, 1950-1951
    - Courses at colleges and universities, synopsis of highgrade schools. Report, 1946 February 15
    - Cultural and social sciences
      - 1946-1949
      - 1950-1951
    - Cultural exchange
      - General
        - 1945-1948 (Box 19)
        - 1949
        - 1950 January - June
        - 1950 July - December
        - 1951
        - undated
        - undated (Box 20)
      - Exchange of Persons Program for Japan, 1950 January - October
    - Cultural reeducation of Japan, undated
    - Curriculum, 1945-1950
    - Curriculum construction. Memos, 1949 September 12 and 22
    - Curriculum for elementary and secondary levels of Japanese schools. Report, 1946 November 5
    - Daiwa kindergarten, petitions to prevent closing of, 1951 August 21
    - Decentralization, 1946-1950
    - Decentralization and Distribution of Educational Function, Chapter VIII
    - Del Re, Professor, 1945-1946
    - Democratizing Japan. Article, undated
    - The Development and Present Status of Romaji in Japan. Report, 1950 December
    - Development of Educational Policy, Chapter XXI
    - Development of Elementary and Secondary School Curricula, Chapter II
    - Developments in Japanese Education in Terms of the Report of the U.S. Education Mission to Japan. Report, 1950 August (Box 21)
    - Diet library, 1947-1949
    - Directives to the Japanese Government
      - Index and catalog of SCAP directives, 1947 February, 1949 September - October
      - By date, 1945-1946